>> 我们正在经历人类有史以来建设速度最快的一波热潮。
>> We're experiencing one of the fastest building booms the world has ever seen.
这场全球性的建设狂潮，丝毫没有放缓的迹象。
Described as a global construction frenzy that shows no signs of slowing.
如今，人类已经离不开大规模数据中心（data center），
Humanity is now dependent on large-scale data centers
而且这种需求还在持续攀升。
and that demand is only increasing.
但这些基础设施
But the strain this infrastructure
对电力和水资源造成的压力，是巨大的。
is placing on our power and water sources is enormous.
人们开始注意到这个问题了。
And people are starting to notice.
许多附近的居民直说："别建在我家旁边。"
Many neighboring homeowners say, "Not in my backyard."
>> 这股反对浪潮，正迫使一些科技巨头重新思考——他们[冷哼]究竟该把数据中心建在哪里。
>> That opposition is forcing some tech giants to rethink where they [snorts] should build.
实际上，整个数据中心行业将占全球电力消耗的 3%—4%。
The data center industry is actually going to be responsible for 3-4% of global electricity consumption.
这是个不折不扣的庞大领域。
So, that's that's a huge sector.
随着 AI（人工智能）将我们对数字基础设施的依赖提升到全新高度，
And now with AI taking our reliance to a whole new level,
这个飞速扩张的行业
this rapidly growing area of industry
正承受着巨大压力，必须尽快整改。
is under pressure to clean up its act and fast.
但这些建筑消耗的能源已经堪比整个国家，
But with these buildings now consuming as much energy as entire countries,
我们到底能做什么？
what can we actually do about it?
>> >> 这就是 2026 年一座典型数据中心的样子。
>> >> This is what a typical data center looks like in 2026.
如果你住在大城市或其周边，
And if you live in or close to a major city,
周围很可能就有一座。
there's a good chance you'll have one nearby.
因为全球现在有超过 11,000 座数据中心，遍布 174 个国家。
Because there are now more than 11,000 of these worldwide across 174 countries.
毫不意外，其中超过三分之一在美国。
And unsurprisingly, over a third of them are in the USA.
最大的集群，出现在德克萨斯州、加利福尼亚州这些你能预料到的地方。
Some of the largest clusters are in places you might expect like Texas and California.
但拥有数量最多的州，其实是弗吉尼亚。
But the state with the most is actually Virginia.
英国和德国位居第二、三位，但差距悬殊。
The UK and Germany are way behind in second and third.
其余的则相当均匀地分布在全球各地。
And the rest are pretty well spread around the globe.
因为如果它们不是无处不在，
Because if they weren't absolutely everywhere,
我们就无法完成
we wouldn't be able to do all those things
那些已成为现代生活必需品的一切。
that have become an essential part of our modern lives.
我们可不只是说网购、网银，
We don't just mean the important stuff like online shopping, banking,
或者在 YouTube 上看精彩的建筑纪录片这些重要的事情。
or watching epic construction videos on YouTube.
没有数据中心，就没有刷坏消息停不下来，
Without data centers, there'd be no doom scrolling,
没有那些"完全可以发封邮件解决"的超长视频会议，
no long video calls that really could have been an email,
更没有那些拒绝消亡的表情包。
or memes that just refuse to die.
而那些，我们也没有多想念，是吧？
And we don't miss that. Wouldn't we?
但数据中心并非一直都这么无处不在。
But data centers weren't always omnipresent.
要了解这些设施扩张得有多快，
To see how quickly these structures have been expanding,
最好换个角度来看。
it's best to look at it from a different perspective.
毕竟，做一期关于数据中心的视频，
After all, we can't do a video on data centers
怎么能不深挖一些……数据呢。
without digging into some, well, data.
先来看这张图表。
For starters, take a look at this graph.
它展示了过去 20 年间，全球数据中心
It shows the staggering growth in data centers globally
在装机容量方面惊人的增长。
over the past 20 years in terms of installed capacity.
换句话说，就是支撑所有设备运转所需的总电力规模。
In other words, the total amount of power available for all the equipment needed to run them.
注意到大约 2017 年之后，曲线是如何直冲天际的。
Notice how things went stratospheric after about 2017.
目前总量已超过 122 吉瓦（GW）。
The overall figure now stands at more than 122 gigawatts.
灯光、摄影、开拍！
Lights, camera, action!
为了让你感受到这个数字有多惊人：
To give you an idea of just how much that really is,
欣克利角 C 核电站（Hinkley Point C）
the total capacity of Hinkley Point C,
是英国正在建设的大型新核电站，
the massive new nuclear power plant currently under construction in the UK,
总装机容量约为 3.2 吉瓦。
is around 3.2 gigawatts.
这意味着，为全球数据中心供电，你需要
That means you'd need
整整 38 座欣克利角 C 规模的核电站。
38 Hinkley Point C sized nuclear plants to power just the world's data centers.
而且它们还在继续增多、增大。
And they're continuing to soar in number and size.
这家伙到底在干什么，马克？！
What the hell IS HE DOING, MARK?
在 AI 出现之前，我们已经有了很多很多数据中心。
Before AI, we also had a many, many data centers.
但那时的数据中心往往规模小得多，通常在 100 兆瓦以下。
But those data center data center tend to be much smaller, like less than 100 megawatts.
但现在，一座 AI 数据中心可以轻松达到 500 兆瓦，甚至超过 1 吉瓦。
But today, a AI data center can easily be 500 megawatts or even more than 1 gigawatt.
所以，这种大规模的电力需求
So, the concentration of of this large power demand
以及水资源等其他资源需求，集中在一个小范围内，
and other resource demand like water over small area,
对基础设施来说是个巨大挑战。
that's a big challenge for the infrastructure.
到 2030 年，数据中心消耗的电力
By 2030, data centers are set to be consuming
将超过整个日本的用电总量。
more electricity than the entirety of Japan.
这是 2022 年它们从电网抽取电量的两倍。
That's double what they were pulling from the grid in 2022.
正如你刚刚听到的，
And as you've just heard,
这一增长的主要原因，正是 AI 的飞速崛起。
the main reason for this increase is the meteoric rise of AI.
每次你往 ChatGPT 里扔一个问题，
Every time you chuck something into ChatGPT,
就启动了一个用电量和耗水量远超我们想象的过程。
it kickstarts a process that uses more electricity and water than many of us realize.
就是开个玩笑。
Just kidding.
其他频道或许会那么搞，但我们当然不会。
Other channels trying to imitate us might do that, but we certainly don't.
而当 ChatGPT 每天处理数十亿次查询，
Now, when ChatGPT alone is processing billions of prompts every day,
支撑这一切运转的基础设施
it's no wonder the infrastructure that makes it all happen
必须以极快的速度扩容，也就不足为奇了。
is having to scale up very fast.
到 2024 年底，AI 系统已占数据中心总电力消耗的约 20%。
AI systems were responsible for about 20% of total data center electricity consumption by the end of 2024.
而这一数字，到 2025 年底可能已攀升至约 50%。
Um and that number could have increased to about half by the end of last year, 2025.
总的来说，这些数字正在以极快的速度变得极其庞大。
Altogether, these these numbers are just becoming really big, really fast.
但跟上需求的步伐，才是真正的难题所在。
But keeping up with the demand is where things get tricky.
数据中心的建设，可不是盖一个大厅、塞满服务器那么简单，
Data center construction isn't just about building a great big hall and filling it with servers,
尽管从一些镜头来看确实如此。
despite how it might appear in footage like this.
实际上，里面的门道多得多——
There's actually a lot more to it than that,
这也是为什么目前正在兴建的最大型设施，
which is why the biggest facilities being built at the moment
都被视为超级工程。
are considered mega projects.
首先，你得决定把它建在哪里。
First of all, you've got to decide where to put them.
理想的选址，需要良好的光纤连接、
Ideally, you want a place with good fiber connections,
充足的水源；而对于
water sources, and for the really large ones
那些单独承载数百兆瓦电力的超大型设施，还需要高容量的电网。
that handle several hundred megawatts on their own, high capacity power grids.
这些数据中心消耗的电力，堪比整座城市。
Those data centers, they they they consume as much power as entire cities.
所以你不能随便找个地方就建。
And you can't just put those anywhere.
要找到电网容量足够、
It's It's actually really hard to find power grids
甚至可以开工建设的地方，
where there is sufficient capacity
其实真的很难。
to to even start building a project like that.
到那个阶段，供电能力就成了头号问题。
So, at that point, power capacity becomes the number one concern.
空间也得足够大。
There would have to be plenty of space, too.
不只是刚好能放下建筑那么多。
Not just enough to squeeze the building into.
很多数据中心在设计时就考虑了扩建的空间，
Many are constructed with expansion in mind.
而且往往建成后不久就迅速启动扩建。
Expansions that often follow not long after they're finished and with rapid speed.
这些公司被称为"超大规模云厂商"（hyperscaler，即亚马逊、微软、谷歌等），不是没有原因的。
The companies behind them are called hyperscalers for a reason.
还有一个要考虑的因素：气候和地理条件。
Another thing to think about is climate and geography.
较低的气温，有助于降低冷却难度。
Lower temperatures make it easier to keep everything cool.
而且通常来说，最好
And it's generally better
把它们建在远离极端天气事件
if you build these things away from places where there are likely to be extreme weather events
或自然灾害频发地区的地方。
or natural disasters.
就像其他大型基础设施一样，
You see, just like with other big bits of infrastructure,
数据中心一旦宕机，
if a data center goes down,
就可能引发严重问题。
it can cause serious problems.
我可不只是说错过最新的 TikTok 热梗。
I don't just mean missing out on the latest TikTok craze.
我们说的是巨额财务损失、
We're talking about huge financial losses,
服务中断、声誉受损——
service failures, reputational damage, all the kind of things
这些都是每家公司最不想遇到的噩梦。
that every company absolutely dreads.
除了那些必须全天候运转的服务器机架，冷却系统也是重中之重。
Alongside all those racks of equipment that have to be kept running 24/7, the cooling system is a key priority.
通常，冷却有两种主要方式。
Usually, this is done in one of two ways.
一种是传统的风冷方式，通过地板向服务器机架输送冷空气，
There's the traditional method of circulating cold air into the server racks,
废热则从顶部排出。
normally through the floor
with waste heat exiting out of the top.
虽然有效，
While it's effective,
即便部分空气可以循环利用，
even if some of the air is recycled,
这一过程仍然消耗大量电力。
it's a process that consumes massive amounts of electricity.
另一种是液冷（liquid cooling），
Alternatively, you've got liquid cooling,
随着 AI 时代的到来，这种方式越来越普遍。
which is becoming more common as we enter the AI era.
这种方式——你猜对了——
This method involves using, yes, you guessed it,
利用水或冷却液等液体来带走热量，
liquids like water or coolant to transfer the heat away,
所需电力更少，往往占用的空间也更小。
which requires less electricity and often less space.
但另一面是，
But the flip side is that
所有这些水都得有来源，
all that water has to come from somewhere,
而这可能带来相当大的困境。
and that can cause a pretty big dilemma.
这些水，大多来自市政供水（municipal water supply）。
This water is mostly coming from municipal water supply.
这可能给很多公共供水系统带来巨大压力，在美国尤为如此。
And that can be stressful for a lot of a public water system, especially in the US.
>> >> 大多数供水系统的规模都不大，属于中小型。
>> >> Most of the water systems are small or medium size.
它们本就没有多少富余容量，来满足这些大规模工业用户的需求。
They don't really have a lot of surplus capacity to supply to these large-scale industry users.
那么，面对如此惊人的消耗量，我们能做什么？
So, what can be done to manage these crazy levels of consumption?
许多公司目前正优先考虑液冷等技术，
Well, many companies are now prioritizing things like liquid cooling,
投资自有可再生能源，
investing in their own renewable sources,
甚至资助电网升级，以避免推高居民电费。
and even funding grid upgrades so they don't push up people's energy bills.
另一些则采取了更不寻常的方法，
Others are taking a more unusual approach,
其中一些技术正引发广泛关注。
including with some techniques that are generating quite a bit of attention.
全球多家最大的科技公司已与核能供应商建立了合作关系。
Several of the world's biggest tech firms have partnered with nuclear providers.
这些协议将让数据中心由可靠的低碳能源供电。
These deals would see data centers powered by reliable, low-carbon sources.
一些公司甚至在重启此前已关闭的核电站，
Some are even restarting plants that had previously been closed
或者借助尚未完全成熟的技术——
or tapping into technology that still hasn't quite arrived yet,
即核聚变（nuclear fusion）和小型模块化反应堆（small modular reactor，SMR）。
namely nuclear fusion and small modular reactors.
或者，你也可以效仿欧洲的一些公司，
Alternatively, you could do what companies in Europe are doing
把数据中心建在废弃矿井或前军事掩体的地下。
and build your data center underground
inside an active mine or a former bunker.
这两种方案在安全性和降温方面都非常理想。
Both of which are great for security and keeping everything cool.
但这些策略并不适合所有人，
But these strategies aren't for everyone,
尤其是那些需要立刻交付
especially companies needing to deliver high-performance data centers
高性能、面向未来、超高效率数据中心的公司。
that are future-proof and super efficient right now.
我们说的，既包括新建项目，也包括对现有设施的改造升级（retrofits）。
We're talking about both new builds and upgrades to existing ones.
对于很多企业来说，投资核能或凿山建数据中心并不现实。
For many, investing in atomic energy or hollowing out a mountain isn't really a viable option.
事实上，以所需的速度满足这个 AI 驱动新时代的需求，
In fact, meeting the demands of this new AI-driven era
挑战之大，让人不知
at the speed required is such a challenge
从哪里着手。而这正是 IES 的用武之地。
that it can be hard to know where to begin.
That's where IES can help.
IES 是基于物理学的建筑性能模拟与数字孪生（digital twin）技术领域的全球领军企业，
IES is a global leader
服务于各类建筑类型。
in a physics-based building performance simulation and digital twin technology
for all building types.
凭借其全设施整体化方案，
With its whole facility approach,
用户可以在数据中心项目的
users can monitor and optimize the performance of their data center projects
完整生命周期内，对其性能进行监测和优化。
across its full life cycle.
>> >> 他们可以对从动态 IT 负载、机架布局，到高级冷却方案的一切进行模拟建模——
>> >> They can model everything from dynamic IT loads and rack layouts to advanced cooling options.
并将当地气候条件纳入其中。
All within the context of the local climate.
通过采用 IES 的 AI 就绪设计策略，
By adopting one of IES's AI ready design strategies,
超大规模云厂商可以以极快的速度达到设计容量，
hyperscalers can reach capacity super fast,
降低基础设施决策风险，
de-risk infrastructure decisions, and reduce energy, carbon, and water use
并减少能耗、碳排放和水资源消耗——同时满足日益严格的法规和电网接入要求。
all while staying in line with increasingly stringent regulations and grid connection requirements.
此外，IES 数字孪生
Plus, having an IES digital twin
提供了一个以性能为核心的设施虚拟副本，
provides a performance-focused replica of the facility
其表现与真实设施同步，贯穿从规划设计到运营改造的全过程。
that behaves like its real counterparts, from planning and design to operation and retrofits.
IES 还提供端到端的咨询服务，
Then, there's IES's end-to-end consulting,
这家公司已为全球客户
from a company that's helped global clients
解决数字基础设施挑战超过 30 年。
with their digital infrastructure challenges for more than 30 years.
实际上，IES 已帮助一家超大规模云厂商，
In fact, IES has already helped one hyperscaler
对一座现有数据中心进行了液冷改造升级。
retrofit an existing data center with liquid cooling.
该项目使每机架容量从 10 千瓦提升到 50 千瓦，
It saw them increase capacity from 10 to 50 kW per rack,
用水量减少了 95%，
cut water use by 95%
>> >> PUE（电源使用效率，数值越低越节能）达到 1.16。
>> >> and achieve a PUE of 1.16.
与此同时，在爱尔兰，
Meanwhile, in Ireland,
有 10 座数据中心在 IES 顾问的支持下，
10 data centers were able to lower their space cooling energy loads
将空间冷却能耗降低了约 40%。
by around 40% with support from IES consultants.
如果你想深入了解
If you want to find out more
动态模拟如何增强现有 CFD 模拟（计算流体动力学），
about how dynamic simulation can enhance existing CFD modeling
从而打造高性能数据中心，那你来对了。
to enable high-performance data centers, then you're in luck.
>> >> 因为 IES 刚刚发布了一份专门讨论这一主题的全新白皮书（white paper）。
>> >> Because IES has just released a brand new white paper on that very subject.
白皮书内，你将全面了解
Inside, you'll learn all the ins and outs
如何降低 AI 驱动设施的风险、优化冷却策略，
about de-risking AI-driven facilities and optimizing cooling strategies,
并通过完整案例研究，探索其他企业的成功经验。
while discovering full case studies on how others have made it work.
想今天免费下载这份白皮书、
To download the white paper for free today
了解 IES 的全套服务，
and see the full extent of IES's services,
只需扫描屏幕上的二维码，或点击视频简介中的链接。
just scan the QR code on screen now or click the link in the description.
好了，我们聊了服务器机架和冷却系统，
So, we've talked about server racks and cooling systems,
但在数据中心里你会发现的远不止这些。
but you're going to find a lot more
inside a data center than just that.
还有很多其他组件，
There are plenty of other components,
有些听起来可能相当枯燥，
some of which might sound quite dull,
但其实不可或缺。
but are actually pretty essential.
比如安保、网络、配电等等，它们各自都有自己的能耗需求。
Security, networking, power distribution, etc., which all have their own energy needs.
问题在于，这些庞然大物在全球各地拔地而起，
The trouble is, having these giant facilities popping up all over the world
可能对周边基础设施和社区带来影响。
can have consequences for the surrounding infrastructure and communities.
现在，一些人开始反对这些项目，
It's gotten to a point where some people are starting to oppose these projects,
尤其是在资源有限的地区。
especially in areas with limited resources.
这总是取决于当地的具体情况——
It always depends on like what's your local situation,
比如你们是否面临水资源短缺？
like are you dealing with water scarcity?
是否正在遭受旱灾？
Are are you dealing with drought?
而如果突然间来了一座大型数据中心，
And if you suddenly have a big data center appearing,
它会消耗大量电力，
that's going to consume a lot of electricity
而发电又需要消耗大量的水，
and there's going to be a lot of water consumed
这真的会给当地水资源带来额外压力。
to generate all that electricity, that can really add to your local water stress.
新建项目最集中的地方，已经成为抵抗运动的热点地区。
Places with the highest concentrations of new builds have become hotspots for resistance.
弗吉尼亚州——如今有了"数据中心走廊"（Data Center Alley）的绰号——
In Virginia, which now has the nickname Data Center Alley,
据报道，2025 年有至少 25 个项目因当地居民的反对而被叫停。
at least 25 projects were reportedly canceled in 2025 following opposition from locals.
仅 2023 年，这里的数百座数据中心就消耗了超过 20 亿加仑的水。
Hundreds of data centers used over 2 billion gallons of water here in 2023.
此外，还有关于噪音和污染的投诉，
And there have been complaints about noise and pollution
因为其中许多数据中心仍然接入依赖化石燃料（fossil fuels）的电网，
because many of them are still hooked into power grids
并配备柴油备用发电机（diesel backup generator）。
that rely on fossil fuels and have diesel backup generators.
在美国其他地方，一些人担心自己的电费会上涨，
Elsewhere in the US, others are worried
觉得应对这些影响的措施还远远不够。
their energy bills are going to go up
and that not enough is being done to address the impact.
我们担心公众健康。
We are concerned for our public health.
我们担心当地环境的健康。
We are concerned for the health of our local environment.
这将是一个巨大的能源黑洞。
This is going to be a huge energy drain.
所以，我担心的是他们将如何管理这个问题。
So, my concern is how they're going to manage that.
>> 我们绝不会承受双倍的公用事业账单。
>> We are not going to pay double the amount of our utility bills.
你明白吗？
Do you understand that?
至于未来会是什么样，正如我们已经解释过的，
As for what the future looks like, well, as we've already explained,
数据中心只会越来越大、越来越普遍。
data centers are only going to get bigger and more widespread.
而且这一切发生的速度，比我们以往见过的任何事都要快。
And it's happening at a faster rate than anything we've seen before.
数字化增长并不是新鲜事。
Digital growth is not a new thing.
上一个十年，流媒体、云计算及其他技术全面起飞，
We actually had that a lot already in the previous decade,
我们其实已经体验过很多了。
where streaming and cloud and everything else was taking off as well.
但现在，随着 AI 的加入，我们正在应对一种"越大越好"的技术。
But now, with AI, we're dealing with a technology where bigger is better.
你可以让这项技术的硬件和软件变得更高效，
You can make this technology and and and the hardware and software more efficient,
但近年来的结果是：
but what it has led to in recent years is
那些效率提升的成果，只是被用来让模型更大、性能更强，
that those efficiency gains have only been used to make the models even bigger
然后让它被更大规模地采用。
so they can perform even better,
so they get adopted at an even larger scale.
这就是它与我们之前所见的一切真正分道扬镳的地方。
So, that's where things really break apart from what we saw previously.
>> >> 我们现在看到的这股反弹浪潮，恰恰说明了这些事情确实需要改变。
>> >> The pushback we're now seeing highlights how things really do need to change.
当这些建筑几乎出现在人们的后院时，
While many of these buildings are appearing almost in people's backyards,
受影响的人不能被忽视。
those affected can't be ignored.
社区的反对是一个真实存在的挑战，是真实存在的忧虑。
Community opposition is a real challenge. It's a real concern.
我们必须主动应对。
We have to address it proactively.
我们需要思考如何从基础设施层面，
We need to think about how we can accommodate the new industry demand
容纳新兴行业的需求。
from the infrastructure side.
在电力方面，只要有资金，你就能建发电厂；
For power, if you have money, you just build a power plant,
但水资源，你必须开发新的水源。
but water, you have to get new water sources.
那本质上是有限制的。
That is naturally constrained.
然而，Shaolei 认为，
And yet, Shaolei believes the recent media focus
近期媒体对水资源负面影响的聚焦，
on the negative effects of water use in particular
其实有些夸大，
has actually been a bit overblown
因为这并非所有地方都面临的重大问题。
because it's not a major issue everywhere.
如果有足够的可用水量，
If there's enough available to spare,
它仍然是解决那个最关键冷却难题的最佳方式。
it's still the best way to tackle that all-important cooling problem.
在公众讨论中，这个问题通常被呈现得不太准确。
The way it is presented in the public discussion is usually not very accurate.
如果你看一看某些数据中心，
If you look at some of the data centers,
它们仅在一年中最热的几周或最热的几天才使用水冷。
they are using water just during the hottest weeks
or hottest days of the year.
所以，它们的年用水总量可能很低，
So, their annual water usage could be very low,
但在夏季会大量用水。
but they use a lot of water during the summertime.
对待水资源，更好的解决思路是：我们需要负责任地使用水。
A better solution to look at water is we need to use water responsibly.
如果水是充足的，使用水所带来的好处，不应该被否认。
If there's water, I think the benefits of using water should not be denied.
就像这项技术本身一样，
Like the technology itself, the construction of new data centers
新数据中心的建设已经成为一个复杂的议题。
has become a complicated subject.
我们离不开它们，而且它们绝对不会消失。
We can't live without them and they're definitely not going anywhere.
恰恰相反。
In fact, quite the opposite of that.
但如果我们打算继续建设这些超级工程，
But if we're going to carry on building these megastructures
并以超越以往规模的方式推进，
and build them on a scale that's bigger and greater
than what we've seen so far,
那我们真的必须先解决系统中的一些漏洞。
we really are going to have to work out a few bugs
in the system first.
再次提醒，如果你正在寻找如何让数据中心 AI 就绪并面向未来的指导，
Once again, if you're looking for some guidance
请务必去下载那份白皮书。
on how to make a data center AI-ready and future-proof,
make sure you go and download that white paper.
正是像 IES 这样的视频赞助商，
It's video sponsors like IES
使我们能够每周为你们持续制作这些精彩视频，
that enable us to keep making these great videos for you every week,
我们也非常感谢你们花时间去了解他们。
and we'd really appreciate you guys taking the time
to go and check them out.
一如既往，各位朋友，如果你喜欢这期视频，
And as always, guys, if you enjoyed this video
想要获取来自这个全球最权威建筑视频频道的更多内容，
and you want to get more from the definitive video channel for construction,
记得订阅 B1M。
make sure you subscribe to the B1M.